[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software hello listeners to
another episode of software engineering
radio and here with dr. Oxford House
Maya
welcome to the show yeah so dr. Axanar
schmeyer has a PhD in computer science
from the Ludwig Maximilian University of
Munich he teaches JavaScript for a
company called Eggman out'n he has two
books out there one is speaking
JavaScript which is about a comma script
v and he has the new published exploring
ACMA script six book he's a frequent
speaker and blogger and everyone around
here is very happy to have him here and
he organizes the mini Java user group
and yeah we are currently sitting here
during the JavaScript comp Europe in
Berlin and therefore I wanted to ask him
a couple of things about JavaScript and
especially about the upcoming ACMA
script six that standards before we go
into the show I would like to let you
know we really look into into the
feedback you give us so give you if you
write a comment if you write an email to
team at se - radio dot net or if you
tweet at se radio go to a Facebook or
Google+ pages which is soft engineering
radio just let out let us know what you
think of this show of software
engineering Bradley in general that's
all very interesting to us um we had
already a show on know chess which is
show 230 which you might also find
interesting but nowadays we want to go a
little bit into the language itself
which is kind of behind nodejs so Axl
could you just start by giving me a
three-minute overview of what JavaScript
is right
so javascript is interesting because it
has kind of a an ambivalent nature on
one hand syntactically so the way it
looks is very much like Java but the way
behaves is quite different so the
semantics is more like a scripting
language so when it comes to the
behavior it's very dynamic and very
flexible which actually makes it a lot
of or at least for me makes it a lot of
and a lot of other people makes it a lot
of fun to work with it has the syntax is
surprisingly flexible so it's quite
astonishing that for example you right
now modules and inheritance libraries
are done within the language and that is
something that syntactically I don't
think he could do in Java at least maybe
now but initially he certainly couldn't
so what what you can't do in Java you
say you cannot really find how
inheritance works in Java you can just
do the Java way of narratives in
JavaScript you can do multiple ways of
yeah hurtin absolutely and I think Java
just now got lambdas stuff like that so
all of that gives you a toolset in in
JavaScript where you can way very
flexible and well yeah as you said um
you can even manipulate stuff like
inheritance and so on in in and are very
flexible there too and it is an
interesting mix of functional
programming in the opie okay I'm reading
a quote from your first book which is
like right in the beginning dude due to
its prevalence on the web and other
factors JavaScript has been hard and has
become hard to avoid that's an
interesting statement on the beginning
of a javascript book how to avoid so it
didn't feel like you came into
JavaScript willingly it's not the most
loved language it's not the most elegant
language either
I personally of and it doesn't have a
stand out feature per se but the the
stand out feature of JavaScript is how
useful it is basically and you have
other languages lists that are like
whose syntax is just awesome or small
talk that is syntactically very
interesting as well and you have Erlang
and that has that does well when it
comes to distributed computing so with
javascript is kind of like the standard
feature is that it's there in the web
browser and but over the years the
standard feature now is how useful it is
because there's so much stuff you can do
with it can do shell scripting my own
ojs web apps you can even write well
basically native apps for Windows 10 and
and so on so it's it's just become very
useful now is it that you said okay I'm
anyway I have to work with JavaScript so
I can better start loving it yeah you in
German there's a saying where you say
the appetite comes with the eating like
with eating and with JavaScript
once a chick's was out it was quite
clear that somewhere you had to program
JavaScript and afterwards it became it
became clear that you could use
JavaScript on the server as well so you
could use a single language and then it
just became a language he promised as I
wrote in the book that you couldn't
avoid any more and then why not embrace
it if you can't avoid it but the more
you use it the more fun it is actually
and it is complimented by now by
databases that are basically that
supported natively viola a JSON so it's
it's really become fun okay maybe before
we dive deeper into the language itself
let's talk a little bit about how
JavaScript came about so it was created
in 1995 as I if I remember correctly
yeah may 1995 years yeah
and in ten days so how was it craters in
ten days yeah
so I I think it was kind of clear that
there was going to be some kind of a
scripting language in the browser and
the original idea was that Java was
going to be the main programming
language in the browser where you in
which you wrote the the big components
and then what they wanted to have
additionally is a glue language to
connect the components and in the big
components well through Java applets at
that point in time yes but I think it
was going like the long-term plan was to
do more to have like really basically
program whole apps just with with Java
beyond just applets I think okay and
JavaScript was going to be the glue
language gluing everything together and
that was discussion about using
something else even more like PHP like I
think so
Brendan Eich was and a lot of pressure
because he felt obliged to do better
than some of the other proposals that
were around so he had to do it fairly
quickly and it took him ten days and I
think the main challenge was to
integrate it with the Dom API which was
C++ and to because there's a lot of bugs
so he had to work around a lot of bugs
okay is it I've also heard that he
wanted to create something more like
Lisp and then he was told no it needs to
look like Java so he made it like Lisp
was a Java syntax yeah I think the
initial sales pitch was come to us and
you get to implement scheme that's the
urban legend and uh and yeah in the end
it had to look like like like Java
because that was there was a lot of
momentum at the time behind Java and
they had I think a marketing deal with
was done as well and Netscape at the
time so he kind of
syntactically moved in the direction of
Java but there were other influences as
well so self was a very big influence
when it came to the Opie part of of
JavaScript but the way that functions
and closures are handled is very
reminiscent of scheme how did the the
JavaScript language develop it was in
the beginning just in the netscape
navigator which is the predecessor of
what we today have as firefox absolutely
yes what about the other browsers what
about the time since um so the initially
was Netscape Navigator in November 1995
I think Microsoft afterwards they
started to implement it too and and even
copied the bugs and then Netscape was
kind of worried of Microsoft running
away with JavaScript so they then wanted
to standardize it to make sure that they
didn't lose control to to Microsoft and
a Chris kept one that was ratified in in
June 1997 the Eggman script is it's it's
like a standardization organ yes um so
the problem is that javascript is a
trademark and only mozilla and now
mozilla and originally netscape only
they have a license to use it
apart from oracle that has that owns the
trademark and so when it comes to
standardizing javascript even know every
blake the language is JavaScript
everybody calls it javascript the
standard didn't have the option couldn't
use the word
javascript so they tried to find
something else do you standards
organization is ACMA so they called it
ECMO script and the original thought was
let's that the name was so ugly and but
that it didn't matter because it was
going to were going to be replaced soon
anyway yeah so they they started with
standardizing ECMO script one
there was in 1990 and today we are
talking about
Eggman script six can you walk us
through the version history yes
so the ACMA script one happened in June
1997 and that was relatively basic
initially there wasn't even exception
handling mm-hmm that's why java script
fails silently quite often yeah
so the that was the standardization of
the ten-day language kind of basically
yeah okay in ten days I wouldn't do it
exception handling either so they added
that later on ik musket to I think was
just a few minor edits didn't add much
so I'm doing this from memory no-name
ACMA script three is basically the
language that we know now or is still
very similar to right now the the
language everyone is familiar with is
echo script five ACMA script threes is
very similar and I think Equus could
three is when they introduced exception
handling and a lot of the other stuff so
that one is still pretty dominant and
and pretty like still has a strong
presence then they wanted to do then
they went all out with regard to
features and that was ECMO script for
but that was abandoned because of the
different vendors just couldn't agree
and and it was in hindsight it was it
just did too many things yeah I remember
I forgot in an action script for some
time and this was actually X from Equus
before implementation yeah ever being a
standard right yeah yeah it's probably
good idea they never took it first ton
of features yeah so and some nice one
that in combination they had static
typing I think they had multiple
dispatch even interfaces a lots of crazy
features heat you yeah it's quite
amazing that was abandoned in 2008
and the and you could see that for a
long time there wasn't that much
interest in in JavaScript in 2005 that's
when a Jaques happened mm-hmm and it
took a few years to really epochal a to
really become visible but the the date
of 2008 when it was really when Nick
musket for was abandoned kind of shows
you that JavaScript became relevant
again and that people really really
cared at that point in time and then
they kind of split it into two versions
because they had two camps within the
committee that evolves JavaScript the
one camp just wanted to keep things
simple and the other camp wanted to have
a lot of new features or make it more
powerful and it musket v is kind of the
vision of the camp that wanted to do
like a tiny step forward mm-hmm and and
the compromise was that the the the
faction that one and to have more more
features that they agreed to this to not
be as excessive feature wise mm-hmm
on the other hand the faction that
wanted to have like a smaller step they
agreed to adding significant new
features okay so but this that was all
in an eight-man script five so I can
skip five was a minor upgrade to a co
script three yeah and cleaned it up
added a few like support for JSON yeah
so that was the the - step four did
stuff that could be done relatively
quickly and that's the current the
present-day JavaScript basically and the
the the the feature rates were rich new
stuff comes with Zekman script six so
factors later here so the five was a
clean up let's let's do a few things use
strict was probably one of them yes
which
audience I won't turn on strict checking
so I can't do the very crazy stuff in
JavaScript with requests creating box
and and sixes is the new features we're
gonna talk about and you get warnings
more quickly that's a nice feature about
like you can make properties read-only
but in a prescript ryu and in like non
strict mode sloppy mode you fail
silently oh and if you turn on strict
mode you get an exception so when i
listen you talking you mentioned a
couple of times the word ajax which i
guess most of the people are familiar
with but why is this simple I can make
an HTTP request from JavaScript such a
gigantic step for for the JavaScript
ecosystem why did it make a language
nobody liked your language nobody can
avoid it's about how you write web apps
and if you looked at before if you look
at the traditional approach to
programming web apps that was like my
first web app was CGI based so a common
gateway interface that was how he did it
traditionally I was all very static and
if you wanted the app to process input
and to show output it would always have
to be a new page that comes from the
server so this all the processing
happened on the server and you always
had to submit a form then the server
would do something and send back the
output as as HTML and that was very
static and with Ajax all of all of a
sudden things became more dynamic and
you could run something in the browser
that looked like an on desktop
application and the first time I came in
contact with age and Ajax web app was
Google Maps and at the time that it
looked like magic and in many ways it
still is because you can
just zoom around you can just scroll
around in the map you can you can zoom
in you can zoom out and that's a totally
different class of app that now you can
run on the web which is amazing it's
interesting because it s an undescended
the the feature was longer in the
language and then it was discovered at
some point right
yes it's a combination of techniques and
interestingly it was pioneered by
Microsoft so they're the two main
components are XML HTTP request which is
about making requests in the while you
were running s JavaScript on the page so
you can ask for more data from the
server while the page is still there so
you don't have to open a new page in
order to get data from the server that's
part number one part number two is
dynamic HTML that you can manipulate
what you currently see on the page and
change the the data structure that
represents the page and everything
updates automatically
yeah and dynamically so moving away from
the web a little bit and looking into
the language let's talk about some of
the language features a little bit more
I think one of the things you mentioned
is that the object orientation model is
a different one and it comes from self
what is the object orientation model in
there so when you look at Java and the
the basic entities of opie then you have
classes and you have objects and the two
relationships are the instance of
relationship between an object and its
class you have the subclass of
relationship between two classes and the
main idea of something that is purely
object based as opposed to class based
is
that you only have a single entity and
that's the object and you only have a
singular relationship between entities
and that is the prototype relationship
interestingly though you will eventually
introduce some kind of an abstraction
some kind of them as soon as you want to
have multiple instances of something you
you will introduce an abstraction and
then conceptually things are very
similar to something class-based so even
though you you only have objects and the
the prototype relationship versus more
relationships and two entities to
relationships and to entities in in Java
for example conceptually how you
structure everything is then almost the
same you you then introduce objects the
basically are like classes yeah can you
visualize that with an example so what
what would that look like in business
code these days yeah let's keep it
simple and say a point okay and in in
Java roughly what you would have is a
class that holds the methods and the
constructor and you would kind of invoke
that class via new and it would produce
of an instance mm-hmm so and then the
instance data the x-coordinate and the
y-coordinate of the point that will be
stored in the instance and the instance
would point to the class roughly when so
that you know when it comes to methods
how to invoke methods on on the instance
and in in JavaScript if you look at the
if we ignore how how you set up the
instance which is a bit more weird and
in JavaScript or let's say more
complicated then all you have is you
have two objects
at the at the bottom you have the
instance and the instance and and all
you have in JavaScript objects with the
properties fields mm-hmm
so at the bottom you have the instance
that has two properties x and y and the
object at the bottom points to its
prototype that is situated above it well
that's how you would draw it on paper
and the prototype has the methods and
it's just another object and that other
object also has properties and in these
properties that's where you store the
methods that work the the methods of
point and the prototype kind of above
the instance that's basically the class
in in Java so what I understand it
correctly is the difference is kind of
in Java you just inherit structure you
don't inherit state you don't you just
inherit the methods and the public
fields but not them the value of the
fields neither public nor private in
JavaScript you inherit potentially boos
it's yeah so there's always a separation
of concerns mm-hmm you always have two
parts you have the and that's what the
two have in common and other
- what's Java specific later so the the
the basic point is there's a separation
of concerns and the instance has the
instant specific data and the class or
the the prototype object in JavaScript
and that has the data that is shared
between all the instances
mm-hm and the method is the methods are
the same that net shared data between
all the instances and the x and y that
is specific for each instance what Java
has additionally is type information and
so on so right and that is something
that most JavaScript or yeah most
JavaScript engines infer the type
information the what is the use for such
a
prototypal inheritance system it's
simpler a bit so it's explained why and
it's not well as I said before and it's
not drastically different from from when
it comes to how you structure things you
end up with something very similar all
you have is just a okay
so one advantage is you can start with
an instance right away so you don't have
the singleton pattern is kind of a
workaround in Java around the fact that
sometimes you just want a single
instance you don't want to have to
create a class for that so so that is an
advantage of prototype based
object-oriented languages they start
with an object you play with the object
and then you introduce abstractions as
you go along so it's a bit more
constructive a bit more explorative and
it's a tiny bit conceptually simpler
because all there is is objects there
are no classes there is no sub classing
okay javascript is also a functional
programming language how can I see that
so one thing is that if you if you
return something from from from Java
from a method let's say an instance of
an in a class or something you have the
connection to the surrounding variables
but you have to make all of those final
otherwise it doesn't work
and with JavaScript you have more
flexibility so the connection stays live
and you can use those two to store state
that changes so there you have more
flexibility and that enables you to that
allows you to do stuff like currying and
so much more easily yeah tinkering was
part of the Haskell episode which we had
very long ago I don't know the number by
a PI heart but you can look it up
if you if you want to know more what is
so nice about JavaScript this function
or is it nice to be a function language
for JavaScript so for me the main thing
is to just have top-level and I'm
comparing to Java because that's what
I'm the language apart from JavaScript
the most I'm most familiar with
so the NLA i've also programmed a lot of
scheme and it's compared to scheme it's
nice to have objects i like that even
though you can add an object system to
scheme it's not as as built in compared
to java I enjoy having functions at the
top level but that's really not that's
actually I think job is more of an
outlier because if you look at at C++
and and most other opie languages do
have top-level functions so having
programmed Java for quite a long time I
love to having top-level functions in
JavaScript apart from that I always try
yet and some of the array methods that
are very functional so you have map you
have filter and these are just awesome
but in general I try to keep the
functional programming stuff simple
because you can't do a lot of very
clever things with functional
programming but I find that if you if
you're too clever then things are harder
to understand later on so if I revisit
code that I have written even with stuff
that's not as exotic like reduce hmm
even if I visit code that I've that uses
reduced later on it always takes me a
while to figure out what I what I was
thinking when I wrote the code so I keep
it simple but stuff like map and filter
and so on these are just brilliant and
the map function is functional because
you have a function or array yeah it's
called map and you pass it a function
and it applies to all of its elements
it's only convenient kind of soda I mean
there's a lot of definitions for what
function of program actually is but but
one key ingredient is always higher
order functions passing functions to
functions functions as a parameter yeah
alright as parameters another property
of JavaScript and in my opinion one
which makes it so simple is that it's
single threaded so you never have you
cannot create a new thread what does
that like mean in a day-to-day business
what is what is the what is this irizar
the restrictions and what are the
workarounds or what other things that
come out of that yes so interestingly
the simplicity of JavaScript in that
area is now our virtue and when it came
to picking a language for foreign ogs
javascript was chosen because it didn't
have as much capabilities yet and it
didn't have a big runtime library so it
didn't come with with baggage mm-hmm and
no chess is fascinating because it is
very much multi-threaded our so there's
a lot of parallel ISM there concurrency
it's just that you have a single thread
that feeds tasks to something that is
multi-threaded so that is that is
fascinating and right now in the
in the browser you have web workers so
you can you can do multi-threading if
you want to the key thing is that the
the tc39 the committee that evolves
javascript they want to avoid
introducing locks and things to
javascript that makes it difficult that
lets you write code that is prone to
deadlocks and stuff hmm
so they they still in the process and
it's the ideas are evolving there will
definitely be more multi-threading in in
the future of JavaScript and there
already is with what with web workers
and with web workers now that is a new
feature that is called locking array
buffers if I remember correctly in
Greybull yeah and that was introduced
for as in GS to make it easier to
compile C++ code to to JavaScript
Esmond Reyes is um Azen jess is um orbit
I finished the array buffer thing first
and then we get to ask Jess and that
allows you to block then right now you
you don't block and that lets you avoid
deadlocks and the
so a technique that JavaScript uses
often is callbacks hmm
so the there's there's a queue a can
processed by the event loops by the so
called event loop in the browser that is
a single thread and in the queue there's
code two to process and whenever
something happens for example on click
then that is put into the queue and the
queue is is kind of processed one task
little piece of code at a time and with
the with callbacks the browser can be
mathy threaded in the background and as
soon as a result is there there's no
blocking but instead you put the call
the invocation of the callback you put
that in you and once the other
stuff in front of it is has been
processed you can the callback is
invoked and then it can go on dealing
with the results from the from the
computation that happened in the
background yeah so it's basically you
you give the on clicked hand or a
function and say whenever you get a
click event please execute that yes and
DEF therefore your platform around you
can be multi-threaded if you don't write
by this episode so you you get away with
the simple single threaded code simple
model and the the platform is doing all
the hard threading work for you exactly
and you use your queue so it's it's
really easy to to figure out and as a
model is really simple so yeah as I'm
Jess just short what is it as yes so
after a while people figured out that
there is certain patterns that you can
use in JavaScript that result in really
fast code and if you use these patterns
you can compile C++ to JavaScript and
you get with
newer versions of Firefox you get I
think 70% of native speed which is
pretty amazing yeah and what that is is
basically a bit like bytecode but
expressed is JavaScript mm-hm and right
now a more recent development is called
web assembly and that puts this kind of
stuff doesn't store it as JavaScript
source code anymore but as a binary
format but the structure is still a
syntax tree is still a tree and that
will give the web a binary format and
then in the long term but it still sits
on top of the JavaScript engine
infrastructure and profits from the
optimizations and from the cleverness of
that engine and because it sits on top
of the of current engines it's very or
it's relatively easy to implement as
opposed to starting from scratch okay
maybe two SEC race loli into the ACMA
script six and and what is it what is it
is all about I often hear the phrase and
I might have been guilty of saying it
myself back in the past that javascript
is no real language what makes that
feeling and does ACMA scripts fix
anything to change that I think it's
always been it's just been very
unorthodox JavaScript but if you but
what you have to do is you have to take
some time to really get acquainted with
the language and then if you have if you
uses a certain kind of like clever
dynamic coding style and and some
techniques that are idiomatic that take
into consideration the the nature of
JavaScript then you can get a lot of
work done and then programming
JavaScript has always been a lot of fun
and it got more fun with all the support
by all the surrounding technologies the
more it got supported the more fun it
was and the more more capable the
browser became the more other
technologies connected like I previously
mentioned some of the know SQL databases
yeah
a few pieces were missing I think the
main pieces or modules and but those
were added within the language quite
cleverly and you have two competing
standards you have a comment she asked
it's originally was more like was used
on the server more and then you had then
you have a MD that is originated in the
browser and is asynchronous and comment
yes is synchronous oh yeah so AMD if I
remember it correctly you always have to
do one extra function per module you
include so you nest your the module is a
function call basically there's a-- yes
because you need to wait for something
and the only way to wait or not really
to wait because it's single for every
but to to like make sure you get the
resources is this callback mechanism
I guess that is part of the reason the
other part is that it works without eval
yeah see can with no chess or commonjs
modules what you basically what you do
is if you you transpile it to something
else because out of the box the syntax
doesn't work so you have to wrap
something around it you have to use eval
you have it doesn't end with with AMD
you can't just execute the the file you
don't have to manipulate the source code
yeah you can't just execute the file and
it works immediately and so modules get
standardized with segment script six
yeah so now there's a built in modules
of built in which is great and the main
advantage of that is it's it's not that
the brings something to the language
that wasn't there before
because comma chance in AMD they work
quite nicely but a big advantage is that
well performance will get better it's
easier to statically analyze source code
because the structure is more static
less dynamic so tools will profit
but all those are well they're nice but
they're not like radically better but
the main advantage is that the community
like this is now a single standard for
modules and that'll be great
yeah and it's it's if I understand it
correctly it's again that the syntax is
put out there but the implementations
like v8 was no js' or the Chrome browser
or Firefox will have different ways of
serving you that module is that correct
yeah you have two parts basically you
have the syntax mhm and that one is done
that one is standardized now and on the
other hand you have the app aromatic
loader API way can configure what
happens when a module is loaded and how
it is loaded how module IDs are resolved
that kind of thing and that is work in
progress that is still being worked on
and that is separate from the ACMA
script six specification that's a
separate what are some other new
features of the script six would you
like to mention yeah so um if you look
at it is six features they're three
broad categories category one is there
is better syntax for existing features
and two examples are classes which well
inheritance was there beforehand so that
didn't add anything significant but
again standardization matters and an ID
ease profit from having a single
standard for for doing inheritance
because then you can IDs have an easier
time of analyzing source code so how
does it change from before before you
had a constructor function uh-huh and
you could call new on a function which
was always a bit weird yes how is it how
is it looking no classes are
syntactic sugar for constructive
functions okay with built-in support for
sub classing mm-hmm okay but the in the
end the subclass will still be
prototypal inheritance oh you even if
you define a class what you're really
doing is a constructor function on you
defining a project oh yeah absolutely
yeah so not that much changes with
classes and the only classes by name not
by nature okay and if you do a if you if
you do a type of of a class
the result is function funny
so that's category one is better syntax
for an existing feature features
category two is a better standard
library so they add a few things a nice
one is maps and sense because at the
moment you're always abusing objects as
as maps which is mm yeah which I don't
like because you run two problems
there's like you you have to be careful
with the the key on the squanders called
proto underscore underscore because that
triggers magic being a trait is like
special behavior you have to be careful
with inheritance and so on so if you're
careful you can use them as maps from
from strings to arbitrary values but
it's it's better to and you can't use
methods anymore because those may be
entries in the in the object so it's and
with maps you finally you get a real
data structure that's dedicated to that
and then let you use arbitrary keys and
you have methods and so that so no
longer just strings of keys exactly
arbitrary even the objects anything now
so that's really nice it's really not
too much to ask for javascript is really
really late when it comes to that
um then you have promises for
asynchronous programming a new methods
for strings and arrays so can you
explain promises because I'm not sure if
those promises are a nicer way of doing
callbacks basically mm-hmm so the thing
is if you move from a normal synchronous
function to something asynchronous you
always the signature changes and you
have an additional one or possibly two
additional parameters that are the
callbacks that for delivering the
results or for receiving the results and
V and with with promises it's a bit like
the signature becomes simpler because
the signature doesn't change and you
return something from the function and
that is a placeholder for the result
yeah
and afterwards you you can you have you
can have a method chain so the method is
then to receive the result and that has
a callback okay so and and what you
think it like error handling improves
because the apart from then there's
always a you can also catch errors and
then you have a single way of error
handling it's not like with if you do it
with callbacks you may get an exception
somewhere yeah or you may get a failure
and then the failure callback is called
or an error code is handed to you yeah
and with promises there's a single way
of error handling it's always the error
callback yeah so rather than calling a
function and giving it a callback or
more callbacks to do error handling I'd
call the function get a result and all
in there I can supply the callbacks to
do this stuff
exactly yeah so it's not radically
different from callbacks it's a bit
nicer and you
can chain stuff so you it's but it's not
like if you code callbacks properly then
you can already get pretty close to what
promises are doing and so well as I said
error handling is an advantage and it's
again it's a standard yeah right now
there's so many conventions xml
httprequest works differently from some
of the notes ASAP eyes and so on and and
slowly everybody is moving in the
direction of promises so there'll be a
single mechanism yeah it sounds a little
bit similar to futures and absolutely
yes where comes from absolutely okay so
you said we have maps and sets we have
promises and we have new messes on
string so the third category is
completely new features mm-hmm and and
with the the barest additions to the
standard library there's also a shim
that you can use and then you can use
those in engelska 5 just as well so
there's shim is a small library
it's backporting serving basically from
a future version or from the current
version to an older version and that
gives you maps and gives you stuff like
for Strings starts with and and that
kind of like tiny little improvements
yeah the completely new features are
like the main ones I think are
generators proxies in wheat maps yeah
yeah then let's go through all of them
so what what does it generator it's a
very complex features it does a lot of
things at the same time yeah the
I think the construct it corresponds to
the traditional construct it corresponds
to is our co-routines mm-hmm and apart
from like it's a it's it's a feature
that javascript or echo script takes a
borrowed from Python so generators are
come from Python and there's a lot of
good literature in like written by
Python people on generators so what it
is is a piece of code and that piece of
code can say yield at any time at which
point it's paused and kind of goes to
sleep and then you can wake it up later
on and it continues its computation yeah
what's the task you would do with
something like that so there are two
interesting things one is it helps with
implementing iterators mm-hmm so if you
an iterator it basically is well often
it's implemented as a method but it's a
function that you call repeatedly and
that produces one element at a time for
a data structure and then lets you treat
a lot of data structures the same way
trees or lists or what-have-you
so if you want to enumerate the elements
of for example of of a tree one element
at a time manually it's a bit painful if
if you if the function is called
repeatedly des has to remember where it
is within the tree in order to keep
going correctly if on the other hand if
you do it via recursion its
simple - - like if you use a recursion
to visit all the nodes of a tree that's
nice and with with a generator what you
can do is you visit the nodes of the
tree via recursion and then every time
you are at a node you say yield and the
recursion stops here and the next time
it comes Hawes's yeah and after that it
comes back and with the yield you can
also return a result you pause you
produce a result and then later you're
woken up and you continue your work you
visit the other nodes okay yeah that
that sounds interesting that's nice
the other thing is for for processing
asynchronous data hmm so you can if you
trigger an asynchronous computation I'm
say a download a file then you can write
all of the code in an in like you can
write synchronous code but you can't
just pause until the result is done and
then you're woken up and you continue
your computation and then you don't have
to deal with callbacks in anything you
just say okay pause now do your thing
download in the background and please
wake me up once the computations is done
and then you can't just assign you can
just say let text equals download file
so you kind of do an angry as in crona's
program without having it look at an
Chronos bit exactly oh yeah and you do
it in a way this kind of asynchronous
computation it becomes blocking again
because the generator goes to sleep and
obviously you have to wrap code around
it and you have to insert the yield and
everything so it's it's not if there is
some some trickery going on but
conceptually what these asynchronous
calls of have always been is a blocking
call
and the callback was just the
synchronous code that came afterwards
put it into into the function and then
it becomes in in functional program
that's called a continuation yeah and
that already gives you a clue what it
does yeah okay yeah it's a bit like go
routines and go right absolutely yes yes
so proxy what is what is a proxy um
proxies let you are objects where you
can intercept the operations that are
performed on the object so it's
metaprogramming
yeah so it's it is basically so I guess
most of the listeners know the proxy
design pattern where you have an object
before another object and is that just
the one loosely related yeah um there
are if I remember correctly there are
the do you mean like proxy design
pattern or do you mean the interface
meta programming thing in Java
no the actually the design pattern in
the gogh book where you say you have you
you have an object which acts like a
local resource and then you have the the
beckon thing
it's very loosely related yeah obviously
because the like proxy is always like
something placeholder yeah yeah um but
it's more like I think the features call
proxies well in in Java it's a it's a
bit more of an obscure feature where you
can have an interface mm-hm and then you
have a handler and the handler is
informed whenever a method is invoked on
on the interface and and you get told
that method a has been invoked with
these parameters is it like mess up the
thing in Ruby the method which is called
when the method is thought uh-huh it's
very much like it yeah so there's the
best were Justices which is called when
that the missile is not on the object
that it's a very old that's a small talk
yeah fired feature so so and it goes
beyond that because it's even if you're
doing
I think instance off check-in things
like it several operations if you just
read a property if you set a property so
a lot of operations that you perform on
an object I and you can listen to those
I have something that is a bit like an
event handler and that allows you well
for all kinds of meta programming stuff
so you could implement data access
objects you could I think remote method
invocation in in Java is implemented by
like the interface proxy thing and
that's another application remoting and
I think it also helps with implementing
the Dom in in JavaScript because Dom has
some strange things that you can't do in
the language and with proxies you get
more flexibility with regard what you
can do in the language okay and weak map
is essentially a map which doesn't know
which is not holding object for garbage
collection yeah so you can put things
into the weak map and it doesn't prevent
the the keys from being garbage
collected okay so it generators proxies
and weak maps are the new features and
all of them seem or all of them have a
steamer on making the language a little
bit more like meta programming I would
say um and they because those are those
you can't easily do right now be good
yeah I hey I have a I have a quote from
someone and I haven't done probably more
people have said it that's why I don't
have a nossa for it but it says
JavaScript is the new bytecode
so javascript is the language we don't
write we compile - is that like is that
serving to this trend or do you think
it's more for the language itself so
that another way of putting it is
JavaScript is the assembly language of
the web yes um that is about to change
with web assembly because they there
were a few features were added to echo
script 6 + + 1 is integer multiplication
mm-hmm that help with compiling C and
C++ 2 to JavaScript and those are not
like in normal JavaScript they're not
good for much mm-hmm so and back then
javascript still was the assembly
language of the web but now with web
assembly there's a split and you have
something that is still hosted on top of
the JavaScript engine but they can add
features that are not interesting to
javascript is a language now hmm and the
generators proxies in week maps are more
features that just elevate the language
itself so that is not something that is
well maybe generators for should you
want to compile something that has cocoa
routines there possibly but those were
really created very much with the
language in mind and not this
cross-compilation thing yeah um all
right so we're running late on time so
before we move on maybe one last two
last questions one is this episode will
be out in early 2016 probably will echo
script six be available to everyone or
is it still in beta early 2000s so the
there are two ways to actually use ECMO
script six the one is natively in broth
in browsers and there's the is-6
compatibility table by by kang ax we can
look up what's available where and I
suspect in early 2016 it could be that
there
the first engines support all of it
mm-hmm but the other way that is very
popular right now is to transpile
compile from egg musket six take from
script five and the the most popular
technologies is babble babble is using
their yeah boy is just a so you feed it
your echo script six by a code and you
get take my script five out yes and it
works really nicely it's you have been
working wizard for a while
I have yeah it's and it's it's quite
amazing how quick adoption has been of a
cryptic scene and all of the new
features and most people like there was
some some sketches initially but most
people that after they start to work
with the new features that are the
feedback I get is really very positive
do you think it has influenced the
development of the standards thus that
the transpiler were so early available
yeah and it will then get even stronger
yeah because it's now a new it's always
been a bit like that but there's now a
new process in place for for the
upcoming versions and a strict
requirement is any feature that is
proposed has to have I think two
implementations okay it has to be
implemented and in order to try it out
and that obviously that that's great
because it's not it's it's being tried
out in the wild and in you know in real
words in the scenarios and you're not
likely to do something like Java
generics which they have which that
which all this of the engineers involved
contra de chillon you consider a bad
idea yeah okay um what do you think will
have the most influence on the
JavaScript community from the new
features so I always have like so my
standard answer here is I think the two
most boring features are going to be the
most important ones and that will be
classes and modules and
a lot of JavaScript people do not like
classes I think for legitimate reasons
but they will they're not radically
different from from what we're doing
right now with constructive functions
and they will help with with tooling a
lot and same thing with modules we
already have modules right now but to
have a single standard will be great so
again like it's standardization hmm but
you take freedom away from the people
who've been doing it by hand all that
yeah yeah okay is there some last thing
you wanna want to say no I'm fine okay
so then I would ask you so I've
mentioned the tube burps speaking
javascript is about echo script 5 and X
prime expect my script 6 is it's about a
group yeah obviously anything else you
would like to promote so what's what may
be interesting to to listeners is that
the complete contents of both books are
available for free online so you can
just go to the websites and the links
will be published on the on the web page
for the Google cast and you can't just
go to the websites and read the whole
book if you want to although you will
probably like it oh yeah no I love
people who buy them for sure yeah
anything else you would like to promote
um well maybe my blog so duality calm so
what I like about blogging is that it's
the interaction I have with the readers
and the if you look at the comments from
my blog post equality is always very
high and it's a very and I learn a lot
through my readers because they give
comments and it's very useful in very
interesting discussions yeah
and you also run technical trainings yes
yes so ik m'naghten it's called and we
hold trainings and well basically
anywhere but then it's obviously it's a
matter
of pain travel costs in alright alright
so you mentioned your block you're on
Twitter
mm-hm and I guess people can contact you
over this exactly here all right then I
would like I would come to an end ID for
the listeners we will have shown out so
every link mentioned I will put them in
the show notes thank you very much axel
for being on the show it was very
interesting thanks for having me
insightful please give also suffrage an
earring radio some feedback and let us
know what you like because we will learn
from it as well so write a comment on
the website or on iTunes
Rajini made you team at se - radio net a
tweet at se radio or on Facebook and
Google+ we are suffering gene you read
is that I'm Johannes from software
engineering radio thanks until the next
time in goodbye thanks for listening SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at SC radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
Lincoln
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of SU radio is
licensed under the creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Applause]
[Music]
you